<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties letter to his Parliament in Scotland, assembled October 19. 1669. Together with the speech of His Grace the Earle of Lauderdale, His Majesties high-commissioner. As also, the answer of the Parliament of Scotland to His Majesties gracious letter.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08725</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R228635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922142</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80922142</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191827</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191827)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2891:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties letter to his Parliament in Scotland, assembled October 19. 1669. Together with the speech of His Grace the Earle of Lauderdale, His Majesties high-commissioner. As also, the answer of the Parliament of Scotland to His Majesties gracious letter.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>Lauderdale, John Maitland, Duke of, 1616-1682. Speech of His Grace the Earle of Lauderdale, His Majesties high-commissioner for the Parliament of Scotland.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 2, 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Savoy, printed by Tho: Newcomb: and reprinted at Edinburgh, by Andrew Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties command."</note>
                  <note>"The speech of His Grace the Earle of Lauderdale, His Majesties high-commissioner for the Parliament of Scotland" has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="modern_coats_of_arms">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>
                           <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Johannis VVhitefoordMackenȝie Armiger.</head>
                        <figDesc>armorial blazon</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>His Majeſties LETTER TO His Parliament in Scotland, <hi>Aſſembled October</hi> 19. 1669.</p>
                  <p>Together with THE SPEECH OF <hi>His Grace the Earle of</hi> Lauderdale, HIS Majeſties High-Commiſſioner.</p>
                  <p>AS ALSO, The Anſwer OF THE PARLIAMENT OF SCOTLAND TO His Majeſties Gracious LETTER.</p>
                  <p>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpeciall Command.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Newcomb:</hi> AND Reprinted at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Anno 1669.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:4"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191827:4"/>
                  <head>His Majesties <hi>LETTER TO His Parliament in</hi> SCOTLAND, <hi>Aſſembled</hi> October <hi>19. 1669.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E do often reflect, with thankfulnes &amp; joy, upon the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Almighty God, for reſtoring <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and them to their former Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Peace: and we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it a further inſtance of Gods goodneſſe, that as he hath filled Our beart with kindneſs towards Our Subjects of that our Ancient Kingdom, and with a Conſtant Zeal to promote what We judge conducible to their welfare; ſo He hath bleſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s with returns from them of Love, Loyalty and ready Complyance with Our Pleaſure on all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, moſt ſutable thereunto: of which our late Parliament hath given ſignal proofs, as wel as Our other good Subjects. And this gives <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s Confidence that the earneſt deſire We have to render this Iſland more happie then ever it was in times paſt, by ſetling amongſt all Our good Subjects within the ſame, a mutuall affection that may endure to all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191827:5"/>Poſterity, ſhall meet with a free Concurrence from you Our Parliment, whom We have called together chiefly for this end.</p>
                  <p>The bringing of theſe two Kingdoms of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> to as cloſe &amp; strict an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion as is poſſible, is the means that We propoſe, for the effectuating thereof: which as it is the higheſt and noblest deſign We can have, for witneſſing Our Royall Affection to them both, ſo the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it will raiſe Our ſatisfaction, almoſt, as high as Our Wiſhes. For by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the hearts &amp; hands of our People, not only our Throne ſhall be strengthned, and they have Peace and Love ſetled amongſt them for ever, but We ſhall have the Glory of Accompliſhing what our Royall Grandfather King <hi>James</hi> of ever bleſſed Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, attempted as the greateſt thing he could deviſe, and wherein be, whowas a Competent Judge, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the happineſs of the Crown and Kingdoms, and wherein He meant to have gloried as the chiefeſt action of His Life.</p>
                  <p>We have fully inſtructed our Commiſſioner with our intentions as to this Subject, and concerning ſuch other matters as ſeem to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to be uſefull for the Conſtant peace and welfare of the Church and State in that our Kingdome. You are to give him full Credit, &amp; he will acquaint us with all matters; and what is farther neceſſary for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to do, will be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily performed. So we bid You heartily farewell.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE SPEECH OF HIS GRACE THE Earle of Lauderdale, HIS MAJESTIES HIGH-COMMISSIONER For the Parliament OF SCOTLAND: <hi>Delivered in Parliament</hi> The Ninteenth day of October, 1669.</p>
                  <p>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Newcomb:</hi> AND Re-printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Anno 1669.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="speech">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:6"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:191827:6"/>
                  <head>THE SPEECH OF HIS GRACE THE Earle of Lauderdale, His Majeſties High-Commiſſioner For the PARLIAMENT OF SCOTLAND.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the Authority of the King, and His ſpecial Command you are here aſſembled in His high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. You have heard His roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Intentions under His own hand, with the chief Reaſons of His cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you together. You have heard His moſt gracious Expreſſions of His kindneſſe to His Subjects in this His ancient Kingdom, and His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of You their Repreſentatives; And I ſhall as ſhortly as I can acquaint you with what I have further in command from my Maſter to ſay in His Name at the opening of this His Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And firſt I am to aſſure You of His Majeſties conſtant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191827:7"/>and unalterable Zeal, for maintaining and defending the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion in this His Kingdom, for which he will conſtantly lay out His whole Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as alſo for diſcouraging and puniſhing all Atheiſm and Profanities, and all that is contrary to true Religion and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. I am further particularly commanded to aſſure You, That with no leſs Zeal and Conſtancie He will maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the antient Government by Archbiſhops and Biſhops, as now it is happily ſettled, as a ſure fence for the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion, A Government moſt ſuteable to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; and well may I call it Antient, for whoever will look into Antiquity ſhall find Epiſcopal Government hath continued in the whole Catholick Church both Eaſt and Weſt, even from the moſt Primitive and Apoſtolick Times: I ſhal not inſiſt on the ſad Calamities and Confuſions which the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and rebellious endeavours to overturn this Government produced in this Kingdom; His Majeſties gracious Act of Pardon and Oblivion forbids the ripping up thoſe ſores which His own Royal hand hath cured, and long may they be buried in Oblivion: Yet ſure I am, the reflections on thoſe diſmal days ought to raiſe no leſs Zeal in the Parliament, and in all good Subjects for the maintaining of that Government as now it is happily ſettled: For, in his Majeſties Name and by His ſpecial command I do aſſure You, He will imploy His utmoſt power in the maintenance of that Government, and will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the perſons of my Lords the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and of the Loyal, Orthodox and peaceable Clergy in the exerciſe of their functions: He will not endure thoſe numerous and unlawfull Conventicles which tend to Sedition and Schiſm, which have been too frequent in ſome few Shires of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Good Laws have been made; and in proſecution of thoſe Laws, the Lords of His Majeſties Privy Council have ſhown their care for ſuppreſſing thoſe ſeditious Aſſemblies; Yea, and of late His Majeſty has graciouſly indulged the planting of ſome who were eſteemed peaceable men, in vacant Churches (though they came not up to the rules eſtabliſht.) It will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that they walk worthy of ſo great a favour: But if after this removal of the very pretence of unlawful Conventicles any factious people ſhal in contempt of His Majeſties Laws yea, &amp; His indulence alſo, ſeditiouſly Aſſemble themſelves under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religious Worſhip, His Majeſty doth Require His Parliament, and all in Authority under Him vigorouſly to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſuch Meetings, and to bring the pretended Preachers, and the Ring-leaders of ſuch unlawful Aſſemblies, to condign and exemplary puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:191827:7"/>
In the next Place, I am commanded to let you know, That I am ſufficiently Inſtructed to give His Majeſties Royal Aſſent to ſuch Laws as ſhall be prepared in this Parliament, for the conſtant Peace and welfare of this Church, and of the Kingdom in all its Relations: But the chief Occaſion of calling this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the proſecution of that great &amp; glorious Deſign of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to a ſtricter &amp; nearer Union. This Deſign was begun by His Royal Grandfather of bleſſed Memory, who went ſo far on towards this great VVork, that in the firſt year of His Reign over Great Brittain, King <hi>James</hi> named Commiſſioners for this Kingdom, who by Act of Parliament were authorized to Treat and Conſult with Commiſſioners for the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> concerning ſuch an Union: And in purſuance of their Treaty, Acts were made for the Repealing of Hoſtile Laws, and the utter abolition of all memory of Hoſtility between the two Nations: And in the Seventh year of His Reign, it was, by the Judges of all the Courts of <hi>Westminſter</hi>-Hall in <hi>England,</hi> ſolemnly adjudged, in the Caſe of the <hi>Poſt-nati,</hi> that thoſe who after the Deſcent of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> were born in <hi>Scotland</hi> were no Aliens in <hi>England,</hi> and conſequently were capable, not only of Land, but of all other Immunities, as if they had been born in <hi>England,</hi> ſo much was done in King <hi>James</hi> his time. And the occaſions of His Majeſties Reſolutions to proſecute this great Work, were theſe Complaints having been made to His Majeſty, That ſince the 25th day of <hi>March,</hi> in the Twelfth year of His Reign, new duties were impoſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> upon divers Commodities of the growth, production, and manufacture of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and incapacities laid upon the Subjects of <hi>Scotland:</hi> It pleaſed the King to appoint divers Meetings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Matter, though without Succeſs: whereupon the late Parliament of this Kingdom impoſed, in their third Seſſion <hi>Ann.</hi> 1663. great Duties upon the Commodities of the growth, production, or manufacture of <hi>England,</hi> which by His Majeſties Command were ſuſpended, and have not been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, though the Duties in <hi>England</hi> ſtill continue; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on His Majeſties recommendation to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> an act was lately made for ſetling freedom and intercourſe of Trade between the two Kingdomes: Whereupon Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were nominated and appointed by His Majeſty for both Kingdoms to Treat upon that Affair, who had many Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but produced no effect, unleſſe it were a conviction of the Difficultie, if not impoſſibility of ſetling it in any other way, then by a nearer and more compleat Union of the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. His Majeſty is fully perſwaded that nothing can tend more to the good and ſecurity of both Nations, than ſuch an Union. And finding that in His Royal Grandfathers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191827:8"/>time, ſo great an advance was made toward this Union, and that the continuance under the ſame Obedience for near 70 years, having begotten the ſame common Friends and common Enemies to; both Nations, and taken off a great part of thoſe Difficulties, which at the firſt (notwithſtanding the Union in Obedience to One Soveraign) ſtood in the way. His Majeſty well hopes, that what is yet wanting to the perfecting of it, may be now accompliſh'd, and therefore, in His Majeſties Name, I do moſt heartily recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this great work unto you; and I doubt not, but you will ſpeedily ſend ſuch an humble Anſwer to His Majeſties moſt gracious Letter as may witneſſe how well grounded that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is, which His Majeſty hath expreſſed of you. This day the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> meets, and the King will both Himſelf and by His Lord Keeper make the like Propoſals (as to the Union) unto both Houſes: And I am confident, that Loyal Parliament, who have all along given ſuch ample Teſtimonies of their Duty and Affection to His Majeſty, will upon this Occaſion make a ſuitable Return to His Propoſals. What is farther to be propoſed upon this Matter, ſhall be offered at your next dayes Meeting: and the King doubts not but that after the meeting of Commiſſioners for both Kingdoms, thoſe things will be tendered to your conſideration, in order to the Union, as ſhal tend to the Honour of His Majeſty, and the common good of all His Subjects. Theſe things I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, before I came away from His Majeſty to acquaint you with, and I have ſince, upon another Occaſion, received an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in writing bearing date the 7th of this Moneth; by which I am again commanded, amply to declare His Majeſties un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Reſolution to maintain <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government in the Church. So having begun and ended with this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I hope both the groundleſſe Jealouſies on the one hand, and the vain and idle hopes on the other ſhall be at an end.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:191827:8"/>
                  <head>THE ANSWER OF THE Parliament of Scotland, TO <hi>His Majesties Gracious LETTER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Sacred <hi>SOVERAIGN,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Goodneſs of God, in Reſtoring YOUR MAjESTY to Your Government, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this your Antient Kingdome to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Liberty and peace, Hath been, and wil ever, with all Humble Duty and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, be Acknowledged, as the greateſt Bleſſing we are Capable of in this World. And, the Many Singular and Renewed Teſtimonies this Kingdom hath ſince met with, of Your Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Care, Kindneſs, and Zeal, to Promove its Welfare and Happineſs in all its Concernes, have 7s;o engaged the Hearts and Affections of Your Subjects, That We can with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence Aſſure Your Majeſty of a Chearfull Concurrence from this Kingdom in Every Thing may Tend to Your Majeſties Honour, or the Good of Your People.</p>
                  <p>We do, with the Like Duty and Thankfulneſs, Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Your Majeſties Grace and Goodneſs, in Your deſires to render this <hi>Iſland</hi> more happy then ever it was in former Times by Setling among Your good Subjects within the ſame, ſuch a Mutual Affection, as may endure to all Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And, ſince the Bringing of Your Two Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to as Cloſe and ſtrict an Union as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, is the Mean Your Majeſty Propoſes: For Effectuating thereof, We ſhall be ready to Give Our Hearty-Concurrence therein: And in Order thereunto are willing that Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be Appointed for this Kingdom, to Treat with ſuch as ſhall be Employed for the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> upon the Grounds and Conditions of this Union: Reſerving alwayes to the Parliament, Tu whom the Reſolution of theſe Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners are to be Return<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, the Conſideration thereof, and the Allowing or Diſallowing of the ſame, as They ſhal judge fit. And, in Confidence of Your Majeſties moſt Excellent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191827:9"/>Judgment, and Great Affection in all things Relating to the Happineſſe of Your People, whereof this Kingdom hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy had ſo many Signal Proofs; We do Freely and Heartily offer to Your Majeſty the Nomination of the Perſons to Treat for this Kingdom, with the Appointing of their Number, Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Time and Place of their Meeting: And, upon ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Pleaſure therein, We ſhall give ſuch Commiſſions and Orders for Promoving of the Treaty, as (Reſerving the Full Determination of all to the Parliament, as aforeſaid) ſhall Witneſs Our Cheerful Complyance with Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Deſires.</p>
                  <p>The Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> whom Your <hi>Majesty,</hi> to the great Satisfaction of Your People, and Intereſt of Your Service, has been pleaſed to Authorize as Your <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> Hath, in Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Name Renewed to Us the Aſſurances of Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Care and Reſpect, to the good of this Your Antient Kingdom: For which We do Humbly Return to Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> the Offer of Our Lives and Fortunes, for the advancement of Your Majeſties Honor and Greatneſs, and maintenance of Your Royal Authority and Government: And in every thing ſhall be propoſed by Him, We ſhall not only give Credit as to Your Commiſſioner, but alſo ſuch Cheerfull and ready Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as may Evidence to the World the Loyalty of Our Hearts: And in Teſtimony hereof, Theſe Preſents are by Warrant, and in Name of Your <hi>Parliament,</hi> Signed by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Moſt Sacred <hi>SOVERAIGN,</hi>
                     </salute> 
                     <signed>Your <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> Moſt Faithfull, Moſt Obedient, and Moſt Humble <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Servant,</hi>
                        <hi>ROTHES,</hi> CANCELL. <hi>in Praeſentia Dominorum</hi> Parliamenti.</signed>
                     <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>22 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1669.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:191827:9"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
